USMAN SALEEM

Tel: (+61) 04 5058 9445 Email: <u>usman@usmans.info</u> Website: <u>https://usmans.info</u>

PROFILE

A driven and exceptionally talented Architect with expertise in the leadership and management of numerous projects, utilising business and technical translation techniques to effectively complete all aspects of the project including the use of programming, analytical and development skills. An individual with the ability to build and manage key business partnerships, overseeing client specifications and managing all costs and timescales, skills and experience that would enhance any forward thinking organisation.

EXPERTISE

- Architect Expertise
- Extensive Project Management Experience
- Client Relationships
- Team Leadership and Coaching
- Understanding Business Objectives
- Business and Technical Translation
- Extensive Academic Knowledge
- Building Key Business Partnerships
- Extensive Multi Site Experience
- Extensive Global Experience

- Web Development and Management
- Managing Complex Projects
- Java JEE Expertise
- Software Solutions
- Architecture Frameworks
- Online Technology
- Budget Control
- Business Strategy Delivery
- Technical Expertise
- Stakeholder Relationships

EXPERIENCE

05/2017 – To Date Java Developer – Flight Centre Travel Group

- Maintaining, enhancing and migrating legacy backend booking engine to new, improved and scalable container based architecture.
- Refactoring legacy monolithic application along with developing new functionality as micro services using Kubernetes, Docker, Jenkins (code pipe line) to achieve true CI/CD.
- Mentoring and pairing with new team members.
- Participating in regular platform health and suggesting and implementing continuous code improvements and paying technical debts.
- Updating projects portfolio (PCI compliant) documentation using Confluence.
- Following Agile, Scrum and Kanban methodology and ceremonies.

Technologies

Java 8, JEE, Kotlin, Docker, Kubernetes, Git, Teamcity, Jenkins, CircleCl, NewRelic, Wildfly, Splunk, Spring Boot, Swagger/OpenApi, Maven, Gradle

07/2015 – 04/2017 Senior Software Developer – Fedelta Point of Sale

- Developed, enhanced and supported Java based n-tier Fedelta Point of Sale (POS) software suite as a senior member of a small and dedicated team.
- Actively participating in web and mobile development and porting of backoffice utilizing Angular 2, ionic 2, Cordova, Android and iOS tools and frameworks. Dev-Ops using docker as build agents to generate Android and iOS builds.
- Lead developer on docker initiative. Converted server application to be docker friendly. Developed docker files to build and connect server and database docker containers.

- Eliminated commercial installer (InstallAnywhere) and designed and implemented ANT based installer framework which achieved a greater product installation/upgrade control and also provided an integration point with Docker containers.
- Implemented in house database replication framework which removed dependency on commercial replication product SymmetricDS which resulted in increased throughput and remove limitation to allow switching to a higher Java version
- Designed and Implemented incremental database (Firebird) cloud backup framework using Amazon S3 Java SDK which resulted in cost effective and quick database backups.
- Implemented Amazon S3 policies to control access to database backup folders and give appropriate access to support staff.
- Enhanced build framework (ANT) by removing dependencies on CVS and implemented Maven based build infrastructure which reduced build time from 40 minutes to 10 minutes.

Technologies

Java, Amazon S3, Docker, Angular 2, Ionic 2, Cordova, Android, iOS, Spring MVC, Spring Boot, JINI, Jetty, Hibernate, Web Services, REST, Swing, FireBird (RDBMS), SymmerticDS, Jasper Reports, IntelliJ IDEA, Continuous integration (Team City), Git, Maven, JFrog Artifactory

07/2013 – 07/2015 Software Engineer III – ABB Enterprise Software (former Ventyx)

- Utilized technical and analytical skills in developing ABB Enterprise Software's next generation of Laboratory Information Management System (LIMS)
- Followed Scrum and Agile methodology and using Model driven approach of software development to deliver project deliverables on time.
- Worked with a geographically dispersed team of about 20 developers in three teams.

Technologies

Java, Flex, HTML, JBoss 5/7 AS, Hibernate, Databases (Oracle), Spring, Model Driven Development, UML (IBM Rational Software Architect), continuous integration (Jenkins)

01/2012 – 07/2013 Senior Technical Support Engineer – Red Hat Asia Pacific Pty Ltd.

- Front line technical assistance to ensure that customers get the most out of JBoss products
- Engaged and collaborated with open source developers to ensure that the findings/bug fixes are available to all concerned customers.
- Developer-to-developer assistance for the JBoss Enterprise Middleware Suite resulted in customer satisfaction.
- Worked alongside in-house developers, fixed & improved code, provided technical solutions and contribute to the JBoss & open source software communities on a day to day basis.
- Provided guidance to customers (usually dev ops, developers and architects) over the phone.
- Developed further expertise in related JBoss technologies. EJB Deployers, HornetQ, SQL and Transactions, Clustering, Security and gain exposure to other software offerings by Red Hat.

Technologies

JBoss EAP/AS 5/6/7, HornetQ, EJB, Servlets, JSP

11/2010 – 12/2011 Software Architect – OpenSCG Inc, USA

- Engaged with USA based clients using On-Site/Off-Site model. Projects involving rearchitecture of JEE and PostgreSQL based projects for horizontal scalability and reducing performance bottlenecks, resulting in increase of transactions throughput and capability of handling millions of users concurrently with optimal response time.
- RPM and DEB packages development for OpenJDK and PostgreSQL distributions.
- Provided customized CRM implementation, reporting servers and improving user security in existing implementation of open source mailing lists manager by managing and interacting remote clients.

Technologies

Java, JDBC, EJB, JEE, Jasper Server, CiviCRM, Smarty Templates, Resin Caucho, Tomcat, JBoss, SubethaMail, Funambol (Mobile Cloud Computing), Google Web Toolkit, Android 2.x, Spring, PostgreSQL 9.0, HornetQ, Amazon Web Services (S3, EC2, SQS), PostgreSQL RPM/DEB installers, Scrum

02/2004 – 10/2010 Architect – EnterpriseDB PK (SMC-Pvt) Ltd, Pakistan

- Direct responsibility for utilising leadership and technical skills in the overseeing of all projects including the design and development of software solutions, utilising expertise within Java/ J2EE, open source and cross platform technologies
- Built and managed key client relationships during the management of all projects and tasks, working
 on site through the accurate analysis of existing infrastructure and rearchitecture of database model
- Managed numerous technical projects including the Postgres Plus Advanced Server suite of installers, integrating framework on MAC OS X, Linux 64, Linux 32 and windows operating system
- Ensured the excellent leadership of colleagues, working continually in line with project and client objectives and utilising excellent global experience
- Completed effective numerous projects within budget and timescales including the re-architect EnterpriseDB Redwood Replicator Project and the EnterpriseDB Management Server Project
- Continually analysed cutting edge technologies, recommending improvements to enhance efficiency
- Selected to join the team responsible for building a J2EE based grid infrastructure for use within stores, utilised extensive technical knowledge including ANT, AXIS, Hibernate, XDoclet, JUnit, JBoss AS and EJB
- Successfully promoted throughout career within the organisation, initially joining as an Associate Consultant and progressing to Consultant Software Engineer, Senior Software Engineer, Associate Architect and Architect

Technologies

Java, J2EE, Struts, Hibernate, RMI, Swing, JDBC, EJB, ANT, Apache AXIS, Apache DBCP, JUnit, PostgreSQL, EnterpriseDB AS and Installer frameworks

01/2002 – 01/2004 Senior Web Developer – College of eCommerce USA, Pakistan

- Selected to Design and develop the company's web portal, overseeing all technical aspects including domains, email hosting and J2EE applications for over 30 institutes within the campus
- Responsibility for the overall design of the student management system, utilising expertise within Java/ J2EE, enabling the analysis of student results on a remote basis
- Successfully created and managed the company's web portal including an online site management system, working with Active Server Pages
- Direct responsibility for the management of all technical matters including the creation of an online testing system, providing technical expertise and guidance throughout the transition period

Technologies

Java 1.3, Servlets, JSP, ASP, Tomcat and IIS

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Java Technologies: Java 2-8, Swing, RMI, JDBC, JNI, Java Web Start, JINI...

JEE Technologies: Servlets, JSP, EJB 2/3, J2EE 1.4, JEE 5/6, JNDI, LDAP...

Framework/Libraries: Spring Boot 2, Hibernate, Apache AXIS, Apache Commons,

Jasper Reports, Jasper Server, Spring, HornetQ, GWT,

Amazon Web Services, Android etc.

Tools: IntelliJ IDEA, IBM Rational Software Architect (RSA), Ant,

Maven, Gradle, Git, CVS, NetBeans, Eclipse, Together 6.0, Rational Rose 2000, pgAdmin, Bitrock, Installshield, Install

Anywhere, WiX, RPM/DEB

Platforms: Databases (PostgreSQL, Oracle, EnterpriseDB, SQL Server,

MySQL, HSQLDB, Firebird), OS (Linux, Mac OSX, Windows), Application Servers (Wildfly, JBoss 4-7, Tomcat 5/6, Jetty,

Resin Caucho, JRun)

Design Skills: OOA (Object Oriented Analysis) & OOD (Object Oriented

Design), MDD (Model Driven Development), Design by

Contract, GoF Design Patterns, JEE design patterns, and UML

Other: Bash scripting, SQL, .NET framework, C#, ASP, ASP.NET,

Visual C++, ANSI C, gcc, MingW, Dreamweaver MX, Gimp

PUBLICATIONS

Developer.com - "A patter/framework for Client/Server programming in Java" http://www.developer.com/java/ent/article.php/1356891 (2002) discussed a pattern/framework for programs that are developed using client/server methodology. Provide a successfully implemented framework for developing Internet enabled applications

Developer.com - "Using XML as application level protocol" http://www.developer.com/xml/article.php/1380861 (2002) Demonstrated ability to use XML as application level protocol while developing network enabled applications. Discusses the pros and cons of XML as application level protocol

Developer.com - "Stopping a class from being inherited in Java, the Official way and the unofficial way." http://www.developer.com/java/other/article.php/3109251 (2003) discussed two techniques to stop a class from being inherited and how to use private constructor to stop inheritance mechanism in Java

Developer.com - "Developing Java Web Services with AXIS" http://www.developer.com/services/article.php/3443951 (2004) discussed how to customise AXIS to develop Java based web services rapidly and hassle-free

BLOG

https://usmans.info – Custom written open source blogging platform and blog posts on various topics.

EDUCATION & QUALIFICATIONS

2018 ICAgile Certified Professional – Agile Fundamentals

2012 Red Hat Certified System Administrator

2006 Sun Certified Web Component Developer for Java 2 EE 1.4 2006 Sun Certified Business Component Developer for Java 2 EE 1.3

2005 Sun Certified Developer for Java 2 platform

2003 MSc in Computer Sciences (Silver Medallist) – Mohammad Ali Jinnah University

(Islamabad Campus)

2002 Sun Certified Programmer for Java 2 platform 1.2

1998 Bachelor of Commerce (First Division) – Punjab College of Commerce affiliated with

The University of Punjab